{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Specify the sequence correctly", "opta": "Grain growth, recrystallisation, stress relief", "optb": "Stress relief, grain growth, recrystallisation", "optc": "Stress relief, recrystallisation, grain growth", "optd": "Grain growth, stress relief, recrystallisation", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Thermoplastic materials are those materials which", "opta": "are formed into shape under heat and pressure and results in a permanently hard product", "optb": "do not become hard with the application of heat and pressure and no chemical change occurs", "optc": "are flexible and can withstand considerable wear under suitable conditions", "optd": "are used as a friction lining for clutches and brakes", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following material has maximum ductility?", "opta": "Mild steel", "optb": "Copper", "optc": "Nickel", "optd": "Aluminium", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An eutectoid steel consists of", "opta": "wholly pearlite", "optb": "wholly austenite", "optc": "pearlite and ferrite", "optd": "pearlite and cementite", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Shock resisting steels should have", "opta": "low wear resistance", "optb": "low hardness", "optc": "low tensile strength", "optd": "toughness", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cast iron is a", "opta": "ductile material", "optb": "malleable material", "optc": "brittle material", "optd": "tough material", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The hardness is the property of a material due to which it", "opta": "can be drawn into wires", "optb": "breaks with little permanent distortion", "optc": "can cut another metal", "optd": "can be rolled or hammered into thin sheets", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Malleable cast iron is produced", "opta": "by adding magnesium to molten cast iron", "optb": "by quick cooling of molten cast iron", "optc": "from white cast iron by annealing process", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Smelting is the process of", "opta": "removing the impurities like clay, sand etc. from the iron ore by washing with water", "optb": "expelling moisture, carbon dioxide, sulphur and arsenic from the iron ore by heating in shallow kilns", "optc": "reducing the ore with carbon in the presence of a flux", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The percentage of carbon in cast iron varies from", "opta": "0.1 to 0.5", "optb": "0.5 to 1", "optc": "1 to 1.7", "optd": "1.7 to 4.5", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The ability of a material to absorb energy in the plastic range is called", "opta": "resilience", "optb": "creep", "optc": "fatigue strength", "optd": "toughness", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Brass is an alloy of", "opta": "copper and zinc", "optb": "copper and tin", "optc": "copper, tin and zinc", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A material is said to be allotropic, if it has", "opta": "fixed structure at all temperatures", "optb": "atoms distributed in random pattern", "optc": "different crystal structures at different temperatures", "optd": "any one of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Closed packed hexagonal space lattice is found in", "opta": "zinc, magnesium, cobalt, cadmium, antimony and bismuth", "optb": "gamma-iron, aluminium, copper, lead, silver and nickel", "optc": "alpha-iron, tungsten, chromium and molybdenum", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The hardness and tensile strength in austenitic stainless steel can be increased by", "opta": "hardening and cold working", "optb": "normalising", "optc": "martempering", "optd": "full annealing", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The quenching of steel from the upper critical point results in a fine grained structure.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "An alloy steel which is work hardenable and which is used to make the blades of bulldozers, bucket wheel excavators and other earth moving equipment contain iron, carbon and", "opta": "chromium", "optb": "silicon", "optc": "manganese", "optd": "magnesium", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following has a fine gold colour and is used for imitation jewellery?", "opta": "Silicon bronze", "optb": "Aluminium bronze", "optc": "Gun metal", "optd": "Babbit metal", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "When the steel is normalised, its", "opta": "yield point increases", "optb": "ductility decreases", "optc": "ultimate tensile strength increases", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "White cast iron has a high tensile strength and a low compressive strength.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "B", "explanation": "White cast iron has a low tensile strength and a high compressive strength.\nSource: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cast_iron#Table_of_comparative_qualities_of_cast_irons"}, {"question": "Dye penetrant method is generally used to locate", "opta": "core defects", "optb": "surface defects", "optc": "superficial defects", "optd": "temporary defects", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The charge is fed into the blast furnace through the", "opta": "stack", "optb": "throat", "optc": "bosh", "optd": "tuyers", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "A small percentage of boron is added to steel in order to", "opta": "increase hardenability", "optb": "reduce machinability", "optc": "increase wear resistance", "optd": "increase endurance strength", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Which of the following process of steel making is in operation at Tata Iron and Steel Works, Jamshedpur?", "opta": "Bessemer process", "optb": "Open hearth process", "optc": "Duplex process", "optd": "Electric process", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The unit cells", "opta": "contain the smallest number of atoms which when taken together have all the properties of the crystals of the particular metal", "optb": "have the same orientation and their similar faces are parallel", "optc": "may be defined as the smallest parallelopiped which could be transposed in three coordinate directions to build up the space lattice", "optd": "all of the above", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Tungsten when added to steel __________ the critical temperature.", "opta": "does not effect", "optb": "lowers", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Silicon when added to copper improves", "opta": "machinability", "optb": "hardness", "optc": "hardness and strength", "optd": "strength and ductility", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The alloying element which increases residual magnetism and coercive magnetic force in steel for magnets is", "opta": "chromium", "optb": "nickel", "optc": "vanadium", "optd": "cobalt", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Cast iron is manufactured in", "opta": "blast furnace", "optb": "cupola", "optc": "open hearth furnace", "optd": "bessemer converter", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The lower critical point for all steels is", "opta": "600\u00b0C", "optb": "700\u00b0C", "optc": "723\u00b0C", "optd": "913\u00b0C", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Haematite iron ore contains iron about", "opta": "30%", "optb": "45%", "optc": "55%", "optd": "70%", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The material in which the atoms are arranged regularly in some directions but not in others, is called", "opta": "amorphous material", "optb": "mesomorphous material", "optc": "crystalline material", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The steel produced by bessemer or open hearth process is __________ to that produced by L-D process.", "opta": "superior", "optb": "inferior", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Crystal structure of a material is, generally, examined by", "opta": "naked eye", "optb": "optical microscope", "optc": "metallurgical microscope", "optd": "X-ray techniques", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Iron-carbon alloys containing 1.7 to 4.3% carbon are known as", "opta": "eutectic cast irons", "optb": "hypo-eutectic cast irons", "optc": "hyper-eutectic cast irons", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The coke in the charge of blast furnace", "opta": "controls the grade of pig iron", "optb": "acts as an iron-bearing mineral", "optc": "supplies heat to reduce ore and melt the iron", "optd": "forms a slag by combining with impurities", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nimonic contains __________ percentage of nickel as that of Inconel.", "opta": "same", "optb": "less", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The heat treatment process used for softening hardened steel is", "opta": "carburising", "optb": "normalising", "optc": "annealing", "optd": "tempering", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The dieing down of a white flame during the operation of a bessemer converter indicates that the air is burning out silicon and manganese.", "opta": "Yes", "optb": "No", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The electric process of steel making is especially adopted to", "opta": "alloy and carbon tool steel", "optb": "magnet steel", "optc": "high speed tool steel", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Iron ore is, usually, found in the form of", "opta": "oxides", "optb": "carbonates", "optc": "sulphides", "optd": "all of these", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The hardness of steel increases if it contains", "opta": "pearlite", "optb": "ferrite", "optc": "cementite", "optd": "martensite", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "In full annealing, the hypo-eutectoid steel is heated from 30\u00b0 C to 50\u00b0 C above the upper critical temperature and then cooled", "opta": "in still air", "optb": "slowly in the furnace", "optc": "suddenly in a suitable cooling medium", "optd": "any one of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Ferrite and pearlite makes the steel soft and ductile.", "opta": "Agree", "optb": "Disagree", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The lower critical temperature", "opta": "decreases as the carbon content in steel increases", "optb": "increases as the carbon content in steel increases", "optc": "is same for all steels", "optd": "depends upon the rate of heating", "ans": "C", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Nodular cast iron is produced by adding __________ to the molten cast iron.", "opta": "nickel", "optb": "chromium", "optc": "copper", "optd": "magnesium", "ans": "D", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "Free carbon in iron makes the metal", "opta": "soft and gives a coarse grained crystalline structure", "optb": "soft and gives a fine grained crystalline structure", "optc": "hard and gives a coarse grained crystalline structure", "optd": "hard and gives a fine grained crystalline structure", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The cupola is used to manufacture", "opta": "pig iron", "optb": "cast iron", "optc": "wrought iron", "optd": "steel", "ans": "B", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The type of space lattice found in gamma-iron is", "opta": "face centred cubic space lattice", "optb": "body centred cubic space lattice", "optc": "close packed hexagonal space lattice", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "The property of a material due to which it breaks with little permanent distortion, is called", "opta": "brittleness", "optb": "ductility", "optc": "malleability", "optd": "plasticity", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}]]}